Hey Happy Father's Day. Good morning. Today's דף Daf is ס"ה, Samech
Hey, 65. We pick up ממש mamash at the at the very
first line of ס"ה. Samech Hey. It's right in the middle of
a
משנה, Mishnah, very, very long משנה Mishnah that started on yesterday's דף.
Daf. Anyway, after discussing where on the מזבח, Mizbeach, where on the
altar the various bird sacrifices would be, it discusses how you do
it, how you do the מליקה, Melikah, how you like the גמרא
Gemara even went into detail about how you actually hold the bird
to then sever the head with the thumb. But also the difference
between an עולה Olah and a חטאת, Chatas, in the fact you
know the עולה Olah not only is the עולה Olah above and
the חטאת Chatas below, but the עולה Olah you would not sever
the head, you would squirt out the blood, right? Whereas a חטאת
Chatas you would sever the head, and you would do the silly
oh, I'm sorry, I'm getting it wrong, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, thank
you, thank you, great correction, I was as I was saying it
I was like, wait, wait, I got that wrong. Okay, thank you.
So, right, so,
let me just double check.
Right, right, thank you, thank you, okay, somebody should be paying attention.
Anyway.
So the חטאת, Chatas, thank you, the חטאת Chatas right, you would
not sever the head. חטאת Chatas at the bottom you would not
sever the head and you would sort of
squirt it out and then squeeze out the rest. The עולה Olah
which was at the top of the altar, you would sever the
head, right, because the עולה Olah you're burning the two parts, you
sever the head, there's no squirting, there's just the immediate squeezing. You
dip the head in salt, you throw the head up onto the
fire, you do the body in salt, you throw the body up
onto the fire. So that would be the basic difference, like again
that the עולה Olah you would totally sever, not just sever the
head but the emphasis also being sever the two סימנים, Simanim, the
trachea and esophagus, whereas the חטאת Chatas below you would only sever
one and the other major and the עולה Olah you would burn,
the חטאת Chatas you wouldn't burn. And the other difference is is
that by the חטאת Chatas you would squeeze the blood would squirt
out before it would be squeezed out and the עולה Olah it
was all basically this emphasis on squeezing out the blood. Okay so
now anyway and then the משנה Mishnah after describing those differences went
back to review the basic stuff from the beginning of the פרק
Perek about questions about לשמה Lishmah and פיגול Pigul and so on
and going through the normal thing as we've seen before except here
pointing out what the critical junctures are. So whereas by the blood
by a like a mammal, like a cow, a sheep, or whatever
goat, the critical junctures are the slaughtering, the catching of the blood,
the transporting it, and the throwing, here there really are only like
two fundamental acts which is the מליקה, Melikah, the severing of the
head with the thumbnail and then the you know well if you're
either the either the squirt either the squirting out of the blood
if it's a חטאת Chatas and the squeezing out of the blood
if it's the עולה. Olah. Okay so those would be the two
acts. So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara and now
it's talking about like when you have you know לשמה Lishmah you
know when if you do have פיגול Pigul thoughts mixed up with
other thoughts, silly just like reviewing things that we've known from the
past. So top of the גמרא Gemara on ס"ה עמוד א. Samech
Hey Amud Aleph. חטאת או שמלקה שלא לשמה ומיצה הדם חוץ לזמנו.
Chatas o shemalko shelo lishmah u-mitzes hadam chutz lizmno. Okay now a
חטאת Chatas like a bird חטאת Chatas like a like a like
an animal חטאת Chatas שלא לשמה shelo lishmah invalidates, whereas a bird
עולה Olah like an animal עולה Olah a שלא לשמה shelo lishmah
doesn't invalidate it, it just means it doesn't count for the owners.
So then the question is can a שלא לשמה shelo lishmah thought
combined with a פיגול Pigul thought derail it from being פיגול? Pigul?
So if it's a חטאת Chatas the answer is yes it can
derail it because that שלא לשמה shelo lishmah invalidates it from a
different
perspective and if it's a עולה Olah it doesn't derail it. Okay.
So חטאת או שמלקה שלא לשמה. Chatas o shemalko shelo lishmah. You
do the מליקה Melikah שלא לשמה shelo lishmah which which derails it,
invalidates it, without making it פיגול. Pigul. ומיצה הדם חוץ לזמנו. u-mitzes
hadam chutz lizmno. And then the squeezing out of the blood is
חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmno. או שמלק ומיצת הדם שלא לשמה o shemalak
u-mitzas hadam shelo lishmah or you did them both שלא לשמה. shelo
lishmah. זה שלא קרב המתיר מצותו. zeh shelo karav hamatir mitzato. So
in that type of a case if that you had a פיגול
Pigul thought plus a שלא לשמה shelo lishmah by a חטאת Chatas
it stops being פיגול Pigul because the rest of it was not
done validly and would have invalidated the קרבן Korban whereas if you
did that by an עולה Olah it would not stop it from
being פיגול. Pigul. Now. לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית למחר. le-echol kezayis bachutz
kezayis lemachar. Let's say you had two
thoughts and one was to eat it out a פיגול Pigul thought
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmno and a what do you call
it and a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo thought okay and they were
about different parts of the animal. So as opposed to before it
was at different stages of the עבודה. Avodah. So if you had
a let's say a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo thought which is not
פיגול Pigul but invalidates at an early stage of the עבודה Avodah
or a late stage of the עבודה Avodah either way it basically
derails and interferes and it doesn't become פיגול. Pigul. Let's say we're
not talking about different stages of the עבודה Avodah early or later
but let's say we're talking about whether you're talking it to do
eat some of it do some of it some way and some
of it the other way, to eat some not at when you're
having that thought but what that thought is about, to eat one
כזית kezayis here and one כזית kezayis there. Okay so where
were we? כזית בחוץ. kezayis bachutz. לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית למחר, l'achol
kezayis bachutz kezayis l'machar, כזית למחר כזית בחוץ, kezayis l'machar kezayis bachutz,
so whichever order it is, כחצי זית בחוץ כחצי זית למחר, k'chatzi
zayis bachutz k'chatzi zayis l'machar, half outside, half tomorrow, כחצי זית למחר
כחצי זית בחוץ k'chatzi zayis l'machar k'chatzi zayis bachutz was the same
in the reverse order, פסול ואין בו כרת. pasul v'ein bo kares.
And in all those cases it's invalid and there's no כרת, kares,
there's no פיגול. piggul. Now the last two cases presumably the reason
there's no פיגול piggul is because it's only a half of a
כזית kezayis intention of חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, so it's just because
you haven't done the basic criteria. But in the other cases, the
reason is that even though you had an intention to eat a
כזית kezayis in the wrong time, the intention to also eat a
כזית kezayis at the wrong place is a different type of an
invalidating thought, and therefore it's a case of it stops it from
being פיגול piggul because it derails it in a different way. אמר
רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, זה הכלל,
zeh haklal, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says no, it depends on the
order. אם מחשבת הזמן קדמה למחשבת המקום, im machsheves hazman kadma l'machsheves
hamakom, פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. piggul v'chayavin alav kares. If your first
thought was about eating the כזית kezayis tomorrow, you made it פיגול.
piggul. And then your thought about eating a כזית kezayis in the
wrong place, okay, if it was at a different עבודה avoda that
would be an issue maybe about לא כרת המתר כמצוותו. lo kares
hamatir k'mitzvoso. This is during this עבודה, avoda, it's about a different
כזית, kezayis, okay, so that he says that doesn't change the status
and it's still פיגול piggul and you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. ואם
מחשבת המקום קדמה למחשבת הזמן, v'im machsheves hamakom kadma l'machsheves hazman, but
if you first invalidated it with the thought of חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo and then you had a פיגול piggul thought, in that type
of a case, okay, even if it was of a different כזית
kezayis or
whatever, in that type of a case,
פסול ואין בו כרת, pasul v'ein bo kares, you already invalidated it.
So for him, at least in this case of two separate כזיתים
kezaysim as opposed to a thought about the whole animal but at
different stages, here he says it basically matters which one came in
first. If it became פיגול piggul first, a different thought does not
change it. We've seen this by נסכים. nesachim. It's just חזרה. chazara.
וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, זה וזה פסול ואין בו כרת, zeh v'zeh
pasul v'ein bo kares, no in either case, this other invalidating thought
stops it from being פיגול. piggul. לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר כחצי זית,
l'achol k'chatzi zayis u'lehaktir k'chatzi zayis, כשר שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. kasher
she'ein achila v'haktara mitztarpin.
Let's say you have a thought about time, it's either to do
a whole כזית kezayis wrong time but two different acts, to burn
a half כזית kezayis at the wrong time and to eat a
half כזית kezayis at the wrong time, that also does not combine
to be a פיגול piggul thought. So this is pretty much everything
we taught about larger animals, it's just a little bit review now
that we're doing about the birds, you shouldn't think that somehow the
הלכה halacha is different. Okay, fine. So now let's take a look.
They could have said
כל המפגל בבהמה מפגל בעוף. kol ham'paggel b'behema m'paggel b'of. They could
have. But they wanted to record the מחלוקת. machlokes. Exactly. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. Okay, now והקריבו. v'hikrivo. Now we're going to look at
some basic פסוקים pesukim about bird sacrifices because since they're not all
even, some of them fill in stuff that's not even discussed in
our משנה. mishna. Okay, so it says if somebody has a קרבן
korban it says מן התורים או מן בני היונה קרבנו. min hatorim
o min b'nei hayona korbano. Yeah, let's read the פסוקים. pesukim. There's
פסוקים pesukim by an עולה ola and פסוקים pesukim by a חטאת.
chatas. Okay, so the פסוקים pesukim by the עולה ola in the
beginning of ויקרא Vayikra when it's describing what type of an עולה
ola you're going to bring. So it's first about a cow and
then about sheep and then a goat, and then it says if
it's a bird, right? So it says יד. yud dalet. א יד.
Aleph yud dalet. ואם מן העוף עולה קרבנו להשם והקריב מן התורים
או מן בני היונה את קרבנו. v'im min ha'of ola korbano l'hashem
v'hikriv min hatorim o min b'nei hayona es korbano. והקריבו הכהן אל
המזבח. v'hikrivo hakohen el hamizbe'ach. ומלק את ראשו. u'malak es rosho. והקטיר
המזבחה. v'hiktir hamizbeicha. ונמצה דמו על קיר המזבח. v'nimtza damo al kir
hamizbe'ach. He should bring it closer to the
altar, he severs the head and burns it
off and squeezes out the blood on the wall. So first of
all the גמרא's Gemara going to point out that's a little bit
bizarre because after it says you burn it up, then it says
you squeeze out the blood. Obviously you gotta squeeze out the blood
before you burn it up. Okay, but notice also that it says,
right, והסיר את מראתו בנוצתה והשליך אותה אצל המזבח קדמה אל מקום
הדשן. v'hisir es moraso b'notzasah v'hishlich osah eitzel hamizbe'ach kedmah el mekom
hadashen. Okay, so then you remove the crop, you throw it to
the where the ashes are. ושסע אותו בכנפיו לא יבדיל, v'shisa oso
bichnafav lo yavdil, you tear it open through its holding onto its
wings. והקטיר אותו הכהן המזבחה על העצים אשר על האש v'hiktir oso
hakohen hamizbeicha al ha'eitzim asher al ha'esh and then burn it on
the fire. So that's the second time it says burning it on
the fire. אשה ריח ניחוח להשם. isheh rei'ach nicho'ach l'hashem. Now notice
also it only says ונמצה דמו. v'nimtza damo. The blood shall be
drained or squeezed out. It does not say והזה. v'hizah. Okay,
right, by the
חטאת, chatas, just to read it to you different, okay, and here
it says, right, what does it say you do with it? It
says by the, so by the חטאת chatas it says, and this
is the end of פרשת ויקרא Parshas Vayikra when it deals with
קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored. It says
ה ח. hey ches. Hold on. Yes, ה ח. hey ches. והביאם,
v'hevi'am, this is you bringing two birds, a חטאת chatas and an
עולה. ola. והביאם אל הכהן והקריב את אשר לחטאת ראשונה ומלק את
ראשו ממול ערפו ולא יבדיל. v'hevi'am el hakohen v'hikriv es asher lachatas
rishona u'malak es rosho mimul orpo v'lo yavdil. You sever the head
from opposite the nape, you do not totally separate it off. והזה
מדם החטאת על קיר המזבח. v'hizah midam hachatas al kir hamizbe'ach. And
here it says you squirt, right, you splatter. והנשאר בדם ימצה אל
יסוד המזבח חטאת היא. v'hanish'ar badam yimatzei el yesod hamizbe'ach chatas hi.
Okay,
so those are the basic differences
besides up and down, right, where it's reversed of the בהמה. behema.
חטאת chatas is below, עולה ola is down, up, here by the
חטאת chatas it says, what does it say? It says ומלק את
ראשו. u'malak es rosho. What does it say? It says ומלק את
ראשו ממול ערפו. u'malak es rosho mimul orpo. ומלק את ראשו ממול
ערפו umalak et rosho mimul orpo. ולא יבדיל. velo yavdil.
Okay, so that's difference number one. Okay, and then it
says והזה מדם החטאת והזה
מדם החטאת ve-hizah midam ha-chatat ve-hizah midam ha-chatat
על קיר המזבח al kir ha-mizbeach והנשאר
בדם ימצה אל יסוד המזבח ve-hanishar ba-dam yimatze el yesod ha-mizbeach אל
יסוד המזבח. el yesod ha-mizbeach.
So this has והזה. ve-hizah. You do הזאה. hazaah. And here's a
ימצה yimatze אל יסוד המזבח. el yesod ha-mizbeach. That's basically by that.
That's by the חטאת. chatat. By the עולה olah it says, going
back to where we were. Okay, it says,
so it says,
first it says מן התורים או מן בני היונה. min ha-torim o
min bnei ha-yonah. We're going to see in a minute what we're
going to do from that. מן התורים או מן בני היונה. min
ha-torim o min bnei ha-yonah. Okay, that's like not about the act
yet, but we'll see that's at least where our דרשה drasha is
going to start. והקריבו הכהן אל המזבח. ve-hikrivo ha-kohen el ha-mizbeach. So
what's that? Like why do you have to say והקריבו, ve-hikrivo, of
course. Okay,
but anyway, if you're going to squirt it on the altar, you'd
definitely have to tell me. So we'll have to worry where about
that,
על המזבח. al ha-mizbeach. והקריבו
הכהן אל המזבח ve-hikrivo ha-kohen el ha-mizbeach ומלק
את ראשו u-malak et rosho והקטיר המזבחה. ve-hiktir ha-mizbeachah. So that's pretty
funny, right? Because why do you have to if after you did
the מליקה melikah I mean no and then it says the funny
is the next part, ונמצה דמו על קיר המזבח. ve-nimtza damo al
kir ha-mizbeach. ונמצה דמו על קיר המזבח. ve-nimtza damo al kir ha-mizbeach.
So here instead of speaking about והזה, ve-hizah, it's ונמצה. ve-nimtza.
Okay, you squeeze it out. That's what it mentions. Okay, but I'm
going to also circle the other verbs here because that's going to
be interesting, what each of these verbs are saying, ומלק והקטיר. umalak
vehiktir, Okay, but the ונמצה ve-nimtza is different, right? Here's the ונמצה
ve-nimtza
is you squeeze, so the עולה olah you fundamentally start by squeezing,
the חטאת chatat you fundamentally start by squirting. Okay, and then it
says והסיר ve-hesir והשליך. ve-hishlich.
Okay, we want והסיר ve-hesir והשליך. ve-hishlich.
Okay, that's about the crop or whatever. And then ושסע אותו בכנפיו
לא יבדיל. ve-shisa oto bichnafav lo yavdil. ושסע אותו. ve-shisa oto. This
לא יבדיל lo yavdil is not the לא יבדיל lo yavdil over
here. The לא יבדיל lo yavdil there is about the severing of
the head. This is about the opening up בכנפיו לא יבדיל. bichnafav
lo yavdil.
Okay, and then it says והקטיר אותו הכהן המזבחה. ve-hiktir oto ha-kohen
ha-mizbeachah. So there's a second והקטיר. ve-hiktir. So here it says you
squeeze the blood after it says you burn it up right at
the beginning it says והקטיר ונמצה ve-hiktir ve-nimtza and then again it
repeats at the bottom והקטיר אותו הכהן המזבחה. ve-hiktir oto ha-kohen ha-mizbeachah.
Okay, so one more time, what do we see here? Just to
point out some things. First of all, okay, this is the blood
is squirted and the remainder is squeezed out. Here by an עולה
olah it's squeezed out. Okay, this is not severed. By the עולה
olah as we said before it is severed because you're going to
offer it up and offer up the head and the body differently,
although again it's not explicit in the verses it's severed. And the
other interesting thing here is it says first offer and then squeeze
out the blood. It doesn't exactly work that way. And then it
says offer again, והקטיר, ve-hiktir. like you know burn it up. So
let's take a look at what we're going to do with all
of this. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the rabbis taught. תנו
רבנן Tanu Rabbanan והקריבו. ve-hikrivo. מה תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? Why
does it say you should bring it? I mean what's even the
point of saying bringing it to the altar? לפי שנאמר Lefi sheneemar
והקריב מן התורים או מן בני היונה ve-hikriv min ha-torim o min
bnei ha-yonah if somebody brings a sacrifice, bring it from the turtle
doves or the pigeons. יכול. Yachol. It uses plural, מן התורים. min
ha-torim. Okay, and maybe it means you bring two from the תורים
torim because it mentions the birds in plural. Right, it could have
just said יביא תור. yavi tor. Why does it say מן התורים?
min ha-torim? And often when you bring an obligatory bird sacrifice, it's
two birds, one is an עולה olah and one is a חטאת.
chatat. So very reasonably, if it uses the plural, I might have
thought יכול המתנדב עוף לא יפחות משני פרידים. yachol ha-mitnadev of lo
yifchot mishnei peridim. If you say bird, you have to bring two.
תלמוד לומר והקריבו Talmud lomar ve-hikrivo in the singular. אפילו פרידה אחת
יביא. Afilu perida achat yavi. You can even bring one bird.
אל המזבח, El ha-mizbeach, to the altar. מה תלמוד לומר הכהן? Mah
talmud lomar ha-kohen? So it says והקריבו
הכהן אל המזבח. ve-hikrivo ha-kohen el ha-mizbeach. Why did it just say
והקריבו אל המזבח? ve-hikrivo el ha-mizbeach? What's הכהן? ha-kohen? Okay, obviously it's
a כהן. kohen. Okay, or I don't know if that's obvious because
it starts by talking about the owners bringing it, but okay. לקבוע
לו כהן. Likboa lo kohen. That's to tell you that you need
it to be a כהן kohen that does the מליקה. melikah. Because
logically you could have thought that if the same way you don't
need a כהן kohen to do שחיטה, shechitah, right you can have
remember you can have a זר zar do שחיטה, shechitah, maybe you
can have a non-כהן kohen do מליקה. melikah. Okay, יכול? Yachol? אלא
דין הוא. ומה בן צאן שקבע לו צפון, Ela din hu. U-mah
ben tzon she-kava lo tzafon, a sheep that is more limited where
you can do it, right? A sheep also has to be in
the north, לא קבע לו כהן, lo kava lo kohein, you don't
need a כהן, kohein, even a non-כהן kohein can do it. עוף
שלא קבע לו צפון, Of she-lo kava lo tzafon, a bird that
doesn't have to be in the north, a bird can be slaughtered
anywhere, okay, where the blood is squeezed out is at that corner,
but it could be slaughtered anywhere. Of course how you slaughter it
without all the blood squirting out before you get there is a
different question, but anyway, okay, אינו דין שלא יקבע לו כהן, eino
din she-lo yikba lo kohein, how much more so should we not
require a כהן? kohein? If you don't require it by a sheep,
you shouldn't require it by a bird. תלמוד לומר הכהן לקבוע לו
כהן. Talmud lomar ha-kohein likvoah lo kohein. Okay, that the כהן kohein
actually is required here to do the מליקה. melikah. יכול ימלקינו בסכין?
Yachol yimlokenu be-sakkin? Now the next question, maybe you need to use
a knife? Who tells you that you use the fingernail? ודין הוא,
Ve-din hu, it's a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, ומה אם שחיטה שלא
קבע לו כהן, u-mah im shechitah she-lo kava lo kohein, שחיטה shechitah
that doesn't require a כהן, kohein, קבע לו כלי, kava lo keli,
requires a knife, you can't שחט shacht with your fingernail, you need
to actually use a knife to שחט, shacht, okay, even though it
doesn't require a כהן kohein it requires a knife, so something that
has higher criteria, so מליקה שקבע לו כהן, melikah she-kava lo kohein,
מליקה melikah that requires a כהן, kohein, אינו דין שיקבע לו כלי,
eino din she-yikba lo keli, certainly you should require a knife? Okay,
if it has more demands. תלמוד לומר כהן ומלק. Talmud lomar kohein
u-malak. Okay, so here we're reading it, okay, that the כהן ומלק,
kohein u-malak, I'm not sure exactly how it's a different דרשה drasha
because both of those are saying that you can't have a non-כהן
kohein do it, but one כהן ומלק kohein u-malak is saying you
can't have a non-כהן kohein do it, the other כהן ומלק kohein
u-malak seems, I mean it's not another verse, but the other point
is not just it can't be a non-כהן, kohein, you have to
do it with the body of the כהן kohein himself. Now רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva clarifies how this second דרשה drasha teaches you the
body of the כהן kohein himself. Okay, some significance, I mean does
it put the עוף of and bird sacrifice on a higher level
than it's required to have a כהן? kohein? I don't know. I'll
say something about what this requirement is, but let's finish רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva's point. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, so we get
כהן ומלק kohein u-malak that it can't be a non-כהן. kohein. How
do you get כהן ומלק kohein u-malak meaning that you have to
use the body of the כהן? kohein? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is going to tell us: וכי תעלה על דעתך שזר קרב לגבי
המזבח? Ve-chi taaleh al daatcha she-zar kareiv legabei ha-mizbeach?
Would it occur to you? Of course the כהן kohein has to
do the מליקה. melikah. How could I even think that a זר,
zar, non-כהן, kohein, could approach the altar? Now the funny thing is,
I don't get it, we just got through saying that you know
the what do you call it that the bird sacrifices, the animal
sacrifices can be שחט shacht without a כהן. kohein. Here's the altar,
here's your animal sacrifice to the צפון, tzafon, the north of the
altar, you've got some non-כהן kohein שחט shachting it, he's right by
the altar. Okay, now maybe in theory maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
thinks you've got a long knife, but I think the difference is
not just proximity to the altar. Here you're near the altar, but
when he says קרב לגבי מזבח kareiv legabei mizbeach it means you're
doing an
עבודה avodah with the altar. So if you think about the bird,
right, although conceptually you could divide it, yeah there's the שחיטה shechitah
and then there's the squeezing out. The reality is that when you're
doing the מליקה, melikah, right at that act of doing the מליקה,
melikah, the bird blood is squirting at the altar. So that is
the עבודה avodah right of, you know, or it's certainly the context
of the עבודה avodah putting the blood on the altar, whereas by
the שחיטה shechitah that's not the way, you catch the blood, you
transport it, then you do it. So but here it's all so
in that immediate context of עבודה avodah at the altar, it's not
just physical proximity, says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, of course it can't
be anything other than a כהן. kohein. So your first point that
it needed a ישראל, Yisrael, you know now you can't be ישראל
Yisrael it needs a כהן, kohein, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that's
obvious, you're doing it right at the altar, of course it's got
to be a כהן. kohein. Okay, so then why does the verse
still say כהן? kohein? So it says אלא מה
תלמוד לומר כהן שתהא מליקה בעצמו של כהן. ela mah talmud lomar
kohein she-tehei melikah be-atzmo shel kohein. To tell you no, but he's
explaining the דרשה, drasha, רש״י Rashi actually says that this the earlier
דרשה drasha was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and now he's explaining himself.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says which one do we learn out
from כהן ומלק kohein u-malak or והקריבו הכהן? ve-hikrivo ha-kohein? Do we
learn out that it has to be a כהן kohein not a
ישראל Yisrael or the body of the כהן? kohein? How can you
learn both? So it seems that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying
that you learn both because the first one is obvious. Of course
you're not going to have a non-כהן kohein do this thing right
at the altar. So the fact that you can't have a ישראל
Yisrael do it, that's obvious. But the הכהן ha-kohein is telling you
it needs to be the body of the כהן, kohein, it needs
to use the finger. Now I want to say something about why
is this, right, why is this that this is different, that it
requires you know, so I'm not sure I'm really going to answer
David's question but like why bird different but like why bird, like
why one is one way, one is the other way, that I
don't know, but versus bird versus a בהמה, behemah, but I will
say the difference of do you use a כלי keli and do
you need a כהן kohein makes a certain amount of sense because
you could say like you know why is it that a sheep
for example needs a knife and this doesn't. Sheep's a lot bigger,
how are you going to do it with... alright, so okay so
first of all obviously obviously physically you need that. But the point
is once you have a knife by a sheep... So that the
knife is your כלי שרת. kli shareit. Now interestingly, I mentioned before,
תוספות Tosafot has a long discussion about how obvious it is that
the שחיטה shechita knife for קרבנות korbanot had to be a כלי
שרת, kli shareit, had to be like a sanctified, you know, temple
vessel, but his assumption is that it does, most of the evidence
is that it does. So let's assume that it does. So that's
your כלי שרת. kli shareit. So once the Torah is saying, you
know what, the act of שחיטה shechita doesn't require a כהן, kohen,
fine, doesn't require a כהן, kohen, but what sort of makes it
this like sanctified act, you know, other than it's also happening on
temple grounds, but what sort of changes the status of the animal
is you're using a sanctified knife. But if when you get to
the bird, if the bird is not going to require a knife,
can be done with a fingernail, okay, well where's your כלי שרת?
kli shareit? Where's your sanctified thing? The כהן kohen himself can be
it. That's the answer. So where's your sanctified thing that is, that
is, that is slaughtering it? So if you're not going to use
a knife and you're going to use—now that assumes you're using a
finger, okay, I know, I'm like I'm not saying but once there's
the reality that there you're using a knife, it allows for it
to be a non-כהן kohen to do the שחיטה shechita because at
least you've got the knife that's sanctifying the animal in the process
of שחיטה. shechita. Once here you've got the reality that you're going
to use your finger, okay, then it requires a כהן kohen because
the כהן, kohen, that finger is the sanctified object as it were.
So that at least explains that. Now why one one and one
the other could just be the physical, the simple thing, you know,
of course that, that Michael said, that it's, you know, it doesn't—again
fully explain why because you could use a knife for a bird,
but anyway it certainly allows for the bird to be the finger,
you know, and the other the other. And you sort of do
use a knife on a bird but not for the מליקה. melika.
You still use it to like, you know, to tear, get out
that—right, that's true. Now the other point also is of course the
point made before which is that because by the animal there's separate
stages, right, there's a lot of blood, you catch the blood, you
transport it and so on, that also removes it, the שחיטה shechita
from the immediate context of the offering of it. And therefore again
it allows for a non-כהן kohen whereas the bird, which is Rabbi
Akiva's point, is right in the context of the altar of the
actual putting of the blood, so that demands a כהן. kohen. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Now, okay, יכול יהא מולקה בין מלמעלה בין
מלמטה, yakhol yehei moleik bein milmaala bein milmata, maybe you can do
the other whether on the top half of the altar or the
bottom half, meaning the מליקה? melika? The מליקה, melika, right, what did
I say? Okay, the מליקה, melika, right, and then the squirting of
the blood actually, what more interests us is the squirting of the
blood. Okay, yeah, the squirting of the blood really, תלמוד לומר ומלק
והקטיר, talmud lomar umalak vehiktir, מה הקטרה בראש המזבח אף מליקה בראש
המזבח. ma haktara berosh hamizbeach af melika berosh hamizbeach. Okay,
so the same way, right, ומלק והקטיר, umalak vehiktir which is actually
out of order, so one of the things maybe the out of
order is emphasizing is the same way you're obviously going to burn,
burn it at the top of the altar where the fire is,
the מליקה melika also takes place at the top half of the
altar. Okay, and
then the חטאת chatas is the bottom, it's the reverse of the
mammals. Okay,
so, ומלק ממול עורף, umalak mimul oref, ממול עורף. mimul oref. Now
where do you do the מליקה? melika? From the nape of the
neck, like the back, like again רש״י Rashi says that the עורף,
oref, I don't know how this fits in the whole verse that
we're עם קשי עורף, am keshei oref, which is usually stiff-neck, but
רש״י Rashi seems to say that עורף oref is the back of
the head. And therefore ממול עורף mimul oref is like, you know,
your neck here, not your throat, but your, you know, the back
of the back of your neck, okay, and that's ממול עורף. mimul
oref. Anyway, you do it from the back of the neck. And
how do you know? It just says sever the head. How do
you know that's where it is? אתה אומר ממול עורף או אינו
אלא מן הצואר? ata omer mimul oref o eino ela min hatzavar?
Maybe it's the throat. ודין הוא נאמר כאן ומלק ונאמר להלן ומלק.
vedin hu neemar kan umalak veneemar lehalan umalak. No, because it says
here—what does it say here? ומלק את ראשו u-malak et rosho ממול
ערפו. mimul orpo Okay, so by the חטאת chatas it explicitly says
ממול ערפו, mimul orpo, which again means the back of the neck.
מה להלן ממול עורף אף כאן ממול עורף. ma lehalan mimul oref
af kan mimul oref. Okay,
so we link it to a חטאת. chatas. אם מה להלן—one im
ma lehalan minute. מה להלן מולק ואינו מבדיל, ma lehalan moleik veeino
mavdil, but there it says ולא יבדיל. velo yavdil. You don't sever
the head, which means you don't cut the two סימנים. simanim. What
does it mean literally you don't sever? I don't know, that's how
they read it. אף כאן מולק ואינו מבדיל. af kan moleik veeino
mavdil. Maybe here it should mean the same. תלמוד לומר ומלק והקטיר,
talmud lomar umalak vehiktir, מה הקטרה ראש לעצמו וגוף לעצמו אף מליקה
ראש לעצמו וגוף לעצמו. ma haktara rosh leatzmo veguf leatzmo af melika
rosh leatzmo veguf leatzmo. Okay,
so no, because again the ומלק u-malak והקטיר ve-hiktir, is telling you,
not only one thing it tells you is top of the altar,
top of the altar, and the other thing it's telling you this
combination is
body and head separate. Now how do you know body and head
separate? The same way you offer up the body and head separate,
you when you do the מליקה melika you separate the body and
head. How do you know that? Where do you see you offer
up the body and head separate? So the answer is because it
says והקטיר vehiktir twice. So why are you burning it twice? So
the only way you can explain why you're burning it twice is
that you've severed the head and one is the burning of the
head and the other is the burning of the body. So once
we know that the והקטיר vehiktir is separating, so the act of
מליקה—now melika you could say you just do the מליקה melika without
separating and then you take a knife and you finish the job.
So it's not just inferred from the fact that you offer it
separate, it's the link: the same way הקטרה haktara separate, the מליקה
melika separate. So for a חטאת chatat, *chatas*, it doesn't mean that
you doesn't mean you can't, it just means you don't have to.
We're going to get to that.
Next עמוד *amud*. Okay, so. Okay. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, והמליק והקטיר
מה הקטרה haktarah ראש לעצמו וגוף לעצמו אף מליקה melikah. ראש לעצמו
וגוף לעצמו *Talmud lomar v'himlik v'hiktir ma haktara rosh l'atzmo v'guf l'atzmo
af melika rosh l'atzmo v'guf l'atzmo*. ומנין שהקטרה ראש לעצמו וגוף לעצמו
*U'minayin she'haktara rosh l'atzmo v'guf l'atzmo*? How do you know that this
is true about the הקטרה *haktara* that it's separate? שנאמר והקטיר אותו
הרי הקטרת גוף אמורה *shene'emar v'hiktir oso harei haktaras guf amura*. Because
down here it says והקטיר אותו *v'hiktir oso* again. Okay? המני אני
מקיים והקטיר על al המזבח *Hamani ani mikayem v'hiktir al hamizbeach*? So
what's this והקטיר *v'hiktir* up here? בהקטרת ראש הכתוב מדבר *B'haktaras rosh
hakasuv medaber*. So it must be there are two הקטרות *haktaros*, the
head and the body are separate. Therefore, the מליקה melikah. *melika* that's
connected to the הקטרה *haktara*, the head and the body are separate.
Sometimes it's like foreshadowing, you know what I mean? I understand, Michael.
ואיזהו *V'eizehu*?
How often do I have to say that I'm not, we're not
interested in פשט *pshat* here? This is the דרשה *drasha* land, okay?
Not the מדרש *midrash*-like stories. Okay. ואיזהו זה קיר עליון *V'eizehu zeh
kir elyon*? Now, if you got to do it up here where
you're doing the הקטרה *haktara*, you got to do it at the
top half of the altar. Which means you're on the סובב *soveiv*.
You're on the סובב *soveiv* actually. Yeah, that we discussed yesterday. You're
on the סובב *soveiv*. Okay, but it's still the top half of
the altar. או אינו אלא קיר תחתון *O eino ela kir tachton*?
No, maybe it still means the bottom half. ודין הוא hu, *V'din
hu*. מה בהמה behemah שחטאתה למעלה ועולתה למטה *Ma behema she'chatasa l'mala
v'olasa l'mata*? A בהמה *behema* that the חטאת chatas, *chatas* is above,
you know, that the עולה olah *ola* is below. עוף of שחטאתו
למטה *Of she'chataso l'mata*. An עוף of, *of* that seems to be
downgraded, even the important חטאת chatas. *chatas* is below. אינו דין שעולתו
למטה *Eino din she'olaso l'mata*? Certainly maybe the עולה olah, *ola* should
be below. תלמוד לומר והמליק והקטיר ונמצה דמו ve-nimtza damo. *Talmud lomar
v'himlik v'hiktir v'nimtza damo*. You sever, you burn it, and you squeeze
out the blood. וכי תעלה על דעתך לאחר שהקטיר חוזר וממצה *V'chi
sa'aleh al da'atacha l'achar she'hiktir chozer u'mimatze*? So I don't understand. How
is it that after you've offered up the thing you're going to
squeeze out the blood? You can't do that. אלא לומר לך מה
הקטרה בראש המזבח אף מיצוי בראש המזבח *Ela lomar lach ma haktara
b'rosh hamizbeach af mitzui b'rosh hamizbeach*. Okay, so
this is Michael, before you were asking when we said the top
of the altar we were talking about the מליקה melikah. *melika* or
the blood. And the answer here is both, okay? So והמליק והקטיר
*v'himlik v'hiktir*. Why is מליקה melikah *melika* before the הקטרה *haktara*?
Well, actually מליקה melikah *melika* has to be before. Okay, but anyway,
so no, just the order. I'm saying מליקה melikah *melika* and הקטרה
*haktara* tells you that the מליקה melikah *melika* is at the top
of the altar, okay, and then also tells you that the מליקה
melikah *melika* is separate. But why והקטיר ונמצה *v'hiktir v'nimtza*? Squeezing the
blood has to happen before. So by putting it out of order
and putting the והקטיר *v'hiktir* earlier, it's actually telling you that the
squeezing out of the blood is also the same place the הקטרה
*haktara* takes place. Okay? So the הקטרה *haktara* is, you know, the
הקטרה *haktara* here is top of the altar, okay? Or top, doesn't
mean top top, top half of the altar, okay? You have to
be at least on the סובב *soveiv* in order to throw the
stuff on the fire. You don't have to be at the very
top. Okay? So therefore, if that's the top half of the altar,
that's true about the מליקה melika, *melika* and that's true about the
squeezing. They're both at the top half of the altar. Can you
see the fire from the סובב *soveiv*? Yeah, the סובב *soveiv* from
the סובב *soveiv* to the top is שלוש אמות amot, *shalosh amos*,
which is four and a half feet. Okay? I don't know if
you could see it but you could certainly, you know. Because like
it'd be kind of awkward if you're trying to throw it in
and like you know just totally miss. Three and a half feet
is like what, it's up to here. Okay? So if I had
the thing that was like up to here and the fire was
there, I could do that. All right, anyway. All right, so where
were we? בהקטרת ראש הכתוב מדבר *B'haktaras rosh hakasuv medaber*. Okay, whatever.
ונמצה דמו *V'nimtza damo* כולו אל קיר המזבח ולא אל קיר כבש
ולא אל קיר היכל *kulo el kir hamizbeach v'lo el kir
kevesh v'lo el kir heichal*. Did I skip a line? Yeah, I
skipped a line when I read it before, I think. Let's go
back to five lines from the wide lines. ונמצה דמו *V'nimtza damo*,
squeeze out the blood, כולו *kulo*. I think I skipped that line.
Squeeze out all the blood. Okay? אל קיר המזבח *El kir hamizbeach*,
by the wall, ולא אל קיר כבש ולא אל קיר היכל *v'lo
el kir kevesh v'lo el kir heichal*. Specifically it has to be
the wall of the altar, not the wall of the ramp or
of the היכל *heichal*. ואיזהו *V'eizehu*? I skipped that previous line. The
line that was A, squeeze out all the blood and B, specifically
the wall of the altar. And now what we were reading before,
ואיזהו זה קיר עליון *v'eizehu zeh kir elyon*? That's the top half.
או אינו אלא קיר תחתון *O eino ela kir tachton*? No, maybe
it still means the bottom half. ודין הוא *V'din hu*. מה בהמה
שחטאתה למעלה ועולתה למטה *Ma behema she'chatasa l'mala v'olasa l'mata*? אף עוף
שחטאתו למטה *Af of she'chataso l'mata*. אינו דין שעולתו למטה *Eino din
she'olaso l'mata*? תלמוד לומר והמליק והקטיר *Talmud lomar v'himlik v'hiktir*. ונמצה דמו
*V'nimtza damo*. וכי תעלה על דעתך לאחר שהקטיר חוזר וממצה *V'chi sa'aleh
al da'atacha l'achar she'hiktir chozer u'mimatze*? Why does it say squeeze out
the blood after it says burn it? אלא לומר לך מה הקטרה
בראש המזבח אף מיצוי בראש המזבח *Ela lomar lach ma haktara b'rosh
hamizbeach af mitzui b'rosh hamizbeach*. הכיצד *Ha'keitzad*? So again, okay? So it's
all of the blood, the wall of the altar. But since it
should have said this before it says offer and it says it
after it says you burn it, it's to tell you that the
same way the מליקה melika *melika* is at the top or at
the top half of the altar, the squeezing out is also at
the top half of the altar. הכיצד *Ha'keitzad*? How does this play
out? היה עולה olah, בכבש *Haya ole b'kevesh*. You'd go up the
ramp. ופונה לסובב *U'fone l'soveiv*. And then go to the walk-around, which
is halfway up the height of the altar. ובא לו לקרן דרומית
מזרחית *U'ba lo l'keren dromis mizrachis*. And you would come there to
the first corner, which would be the southeast corner. היה מליק את
ראשה *Haya molek es rosha*. So there you would do the מליקה
melika, *melika* at the top. at the top half of the altar,
ממול ערפה ומבדיל, u-mavdil, sever it, וממצה את דמה על קיר המזבח,
u-mamtzeh et damah al kir ha-mizbei'ach, and then do the squeezing out
of the blood at the top half of the altar. Okay, now
so it's a nice point, meaning first it's going to go through
the דרשות drashot of the פסוקים psukim and then it's going to
like walk you through, do a walk-through about how you go ahead
and step-by-step do it. Okay, squeeze it out at the wall of
the altar, ומצה למטה מרגליו אפילו אמה כשרה. u-mamtzeh le-mata me-raglav afilu
ama kshaira. And you can actually even squeeze it out an אמה
amah below your feet. Why? Because if you remember the altar, okay,
right? The altar had this was the walkaround, right? Wait a minute.
Right, that's sort of the way the altar looks. Okay,
so this thing, this אמה amah protruding here, right, was sort of
like a
walkaround, right, you know, and so on, right? And this was one
אמה, amah, six אמות, amot three אמות amot here, so here, well
actually no it was like five, I'm sorry, three and then you
had the one like that. Anyway, so this walkaround was six אמות
off the ground, so the middle line was an אמה amah below
the walkaround. Got it? So the כהן kohen would be standing here
with his bird, okay, and he could actually squeeze out
the blood an אמה amah below his feet and still be at
the top half of the altar. Alright, so okay, ומצה את דמו,
ומצה למטה מרגליו אפילו אמה כשרה. u-mamtzeh le-mata me-raglav afilu ama kshaira.
רבי נחמיה ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומרים, Rabbi Nechemia ve-Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov omrim, כל עצמו אינו נעשה אלא בראשו של
מזבח. kol atzmo eino na'aseh ela be-rosho shel mizbei'ach. No, it can't
be at the, it can't be below his feet, it has to
be at the top half, like above, above the walkaround. מאי בינייהו?
Mai beinaihu? Now, this is interesting. Actually in זבחים Zevachim the גמרא
Gemara often the phrase מאי בינייהו mai beinaihu which normally means what
practical difference emerges from their debate? But here the מאי בינייהו mai
beinaihu means what is the core point that they're arguing about? What
is the nature of their debate? Okay? So why are they debating
whether you could be below your feet or not? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Abaye ve-Rava de-amrei tarvaihu, they both
say, עושה מערכה על גבי סובב איכא בינייהו. oseh maaracha al gabei
soveiv ika beinaihu. Because remember, it says the squeezing has to be
right near the burning. So if you're putting it under your feet,
okay, you're actually not in a zone, you're at the top half,
but you're like not in a zone that's connected to the fire,
'cause you know, you gotta get it from under your feet and
above that walkaround and then put it on the fire. You would
have to squeeze it under your feet? No, but it's כשר kasher
to do it. Okay, and since we learned this connection, presumably the
squeezing has to be in a place where it's right in juxtaposition
to the fire. So the question is, are you allowed to make
a little fire here on the walkaround? Okay, so if you are
allowed to make a fire on the walkaround, you could do it
under your feet and then put it right on the fire and
that's considered juxtaposed. Okay, even though it means taking it from under
the walkaround to over the walkaround. But if you're not, then even
though this is the top half, top half here, normally we focus
on top half, bottom half, but sometimes not, like a חטאת, chatas
it's not enough that it's the top half, it has to be
on the horns. So here what we're saying is, it's not this
emphasis, חטאת בהמה, chatat behemah, the emphasis is not emphasizing top half,
it's emphasizing the juxtaposition of the blood and the burning. Okay, and
therefore that's the debate of under the feet, because you don't, it
might be the top half but you don't really have the blood
and the burning juxtaposed. What do you make of that, that like
the עולה olah, and the עוף is the opposite of the בהמה
to עוף, you know, like in terms of the levels? I don't
know, I don't know. Okay, so now, בא לו לגוף. Ba lo
la-guf. Now, okay, now we're getting to, so you've slaughtered it, whatever,
now what you're going to do is tear open the body, we're
going to the משנה, Mishnah, remove, you know, the crop and the
gizzard, throw them to the bottom and so on. Or whatever the
crop. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, והסיר את מוראתו
בנוצתה. ve-hesir et murato be-notzata. Remove the crop together with the נוצה,
notza, which maybe means the feathers, we'll see what it means. זו
זפק, Zu zefek, that's the crop, like the stomach. יכול יקטיר בסכין
ויטלנה? Yachol yaktir be-sakin ve-yitlenah? Maybe you use a knife to sever
the crop from the rest of the innards and just take the
crop, that's the way רש"י Rashi reads
it. תלמוד לומר, בנוצתה. be-notzata. No, with its נוצה. notza. נוטל את
הנוצה עמה. Notel et ha-notza imah. You take
the feather with it, meaning you take it out and you remove
it with whatever part of the body it's connected to. Okay, the
outside feather or whatever. אבא יוסי בן חנן אומר, Abba Yosi ben
Chanan omer, נוטלה ונוטל קורקבנה עמה. notlah ve-notel korkevanah imah. You take
it with the intestine with it. And רש"י Rashi says that the
word נוצה notza according to him means basically like refuge. So בנוצתה
be-notzata he doesn't read it to mean the feathers, but I thought
it means feathers? Yes, but רש"י Rashi gives you a use of
the word נוצה notza to mean a disgusting thing. Okay, so he's
reading the verse to mean not take it with the feathers, take
it with the intestine. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא בנוצתה בנוצה שלה קודר
בסכין כמין ארובה. Dvei Rebbi Yishmael tana b'notzatah b'notzah shelah koder b'sakin
k'min arubah. You only take it with its feather, not with any
other feathers around it. So you use a knife to like surgically,
you know, cut the the the place in the stomach around it,
you know, on the outside body to cut that to cut that
skin that's directly opposite. So then when you take it out, you
take it just with the skin and the feathers that are directly
opposite and you don't take out like a bigger section of the
body. All right. Moving on. ושיסעו ולא יבדיל. V'shisao v'lo yavdil. Now,
it says, right, ושיסעו בכנפיו לא יבדיל. V'shisao bichnafav lo yavdil. You
are you use the wings, you tear it open, the inside, okay,
but you don't totally sever
it. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ושיסע, V'shisa, אין שיסע אלא ביד. Ein
shisa ela b'yad. To tear open, ripped open, I
guess here the word we would use like rip open, right rip
open, it means with a hand, right? So you don't actually think
about it, like tear open, yeah, I guess tear, does tear mean
with a hand? I'm trying to think, if I used that word,
would you think it was possible I meant like with a knife?
He tore he tore the box open. Probably you would think it
hands. He ripped it open, I think definitely means with the hands,
right? Anyway, to rip open. אין שיסע אלא ביד. Ein shisa ela
b'yad. וכן הוא אומר, V'chein hu omer, וישסעהו כשסע הגדי, Vayishaseihu k'shesa
hagedi, right? This is, you know, this was by דוד, David, right?
Oh no, this was by, what's his name, by שמשון, Shimshon, right?
He tore it open with the like you know like you would
tear open a goat. לא הסיר את המוראה. Lo hesir et hamurah.
Okay now, let's say he did not do the stuff of removing
the crop, is the animal still כשר? kosher? So the basic rule
is, if you didn't do something after the blood is done, it's
כשר kosher because the emphasis is on the blood. If you did
something wrong before the blood was done, it's not. Okay, so or
about the blood it's not. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. That's nice pictures,
where'd you get that? That is from a while. Oh, it shows
you the things... I mean, it's very very... yeah, I know, this
was... well, that we had
yesterday. How to do the מליקה. melika Right, how to do the
מליקה. melika, Poor bird. What's he doing? I know.
Here, using a knife to get to the part to get out
the crop. Here's the here's the intestine.
Here's the cut here's the using your hands to tear it open.
Good pictures. Got a good artist here. Okay. All right. Which shows
the other way of doing the מליקה. melika Yeah, I showed that.
Okay. No, that was in the back
after. Okay. Fine. מתניתין דלא כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Matnitin d'lo k'Rebbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. Our משנה Mishnah is not like רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. דתניא, D'tanya, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rebbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon, שמעתי שמבדילים בחטאת העוף. Shama'ti shemavdilim b'chatat ha'of. Actually,
so our משנה Mishnah makes it clear that, you know, you are,
you know, so oh because our משנה Mishnah says not the part
about the עולה, olah. but then it says if you were right,
if it says if you were
מבדיל, mavdil, here it says here it says לא יבדיל. lo yavdil.
No, no, no. I know, I know. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm
sorry. The whole thing about the לא יבדיל lo yavdil is getting
me confused. Back to actually the שחיטה. shechitah. Okay. The משנה Mishnah
says if you did, forget the tearing open of the body. Okay.
That's not our point. Okay. It's whatever. The point here we're going
now we're going back to what the earlier stage of the process,
later in the משנה, Mishnah, after it speaks about cutting open, tearing
open the body, then it says, if you actually did the שחיטות
shechitot in the reverse way, or the מליקות melikot I should say,
if here you did the מליקה and you severed both סימנים, simanim,
or here you did the מליקה and you did not sever both
סימנים, simanim, if you did in the reverse way, right, it's invalid.
Now, we understand why here by the עולה, olah. we don't see
where you know you're supposed to cut both סימנים. simanim. I mean
maybe it's implicit because you're supposed to, right, if you're going to
sever the head, well that's what actually that's what the גמרא Gemara
said. The same way הקטרה is separate, the מליקה has to effectively
separate. It's not just you separated it later, the מליקה effectively separates
the head from the body. So that's how we learned out, right,
that's how we learned out the מליקה is both סימנים. simanim. But
what so fine, so here once you say it's both סימנים, simanim,
obviously if you don't do both it's not כשר, kosher, you didn't
do the full עבודה. avodah. That we understand why if you don't
do both, you know, the trachea and esophagus it's invalid. But here,
okay, you know, fine, I did I severed it properly, then I
just got carried away, you know, and I did more. Why does
that invalidate it? Of course, the verse says I'm not allowed to.
But even if I even if I violated that verse, how do
you know that it invalidates the sacrifice? Right? I just did something
more after I finished the עבודה. avodah. So how obvious is it
that if you actually, you know, completely sever both both of trachea
and esophagus by the חטאת, chatas you invalidate. Our משנה mishna says
you do, but the גמרא's gemara going to question that. So let's
take a look. מתניתין, Matnisin, our משנה mishna דלא כרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון de-lo k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon דתניא, de-tanya, because our משנה mishna
says you do invalidate by a חטאת. chatas אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון, Amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, שמעתי שמבדילין בחטאת העוף. shamati she-mavdilin
be-chatas ha-of. I actually heard that either you're allowed to, I hope,
maybe it means לכתחילה, l'chatchila, probably not, but if you did just
completely sever the חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, you cut both trachea and
esophagus, it's still כשר. kosher. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What's that debate
about? Okay, אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, מיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב
איכא בינייהו. mi-tzuy chatas ha-of me'akev ika beinaihu. תנא קמא סבר, Tana
kamma savar, מיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב. mi-tzuy chatas ha-of me'akev.
Now, the basic assumption is like this: the focus, you would think
the focus is on how to read this verse ולא יבדיל, velo
yavdil, because Michael suggested, how did you suggest how to read it,
Michael? ולא יבדיל velo yavdil could mean either you are not allowed
to sever it, or did you read another possibility? No, I mean,
I thought I did. Which is? You're not allowed to or you
don't have to. You're not required to sever it. So you could
say that's the debate. And if it means you're not allowed and
you did it, then you invalidate the sacrifice. The גמרא gemara interestingly
does not focus on that, meaning, meaning it's just going to, it
focuses on a different concept. The concept is just like this: if
you do a חטאת chatas, just like a עולה, olah. it's invalid.
It starts with that assumption.
So the reason that it would become invalid is not because you
violated this verse. The reason it would become invalidated is when you
sever it, you've now treated it just like a עולה. olah But
now the point is, well wait, wait a minute, besides the fact
of the up and the down and the other stuff, well the
only stuff we care about is the blood stuff. The stuff you
do after is not the focus, right, of what's going to make
it כשר kosher or not. So what are the blood, what way
is the blood stuff different besides the location? So one is how
many things you sever, but remember the other one is the והזה
ve-hizza here, okay, right, and the ונמצה דמו. So the squeezing and
whatever. So if you go ahead and but this also has squeezing
the remainder. So if you both sever it and squeeze it, then
you have done the exact thing as you do by a עולה.
olah. Okay? So that's the assumption why completely severing it will invalidate
it, because you have the severing and the squeezing and you've treated
it just like a עולה. olah So the גמרא's gemara going to
say, well, maybe therefore whether you're treating this just like a עולה
olah will depend on whether you actually have to squeeze it out.
Maybe this is like, you know, the spilling of the שריים shirayim
and so on. And if you don't have to actually have to
squeeze it out, then you could forget doing this and then you
could sever this without making it like a עולה. olah But if
you both sever it and you squeeze it out, then you're doing
exactly what you do by an עולה olah? and that's the גמרא's
gemara assumption of what invalidates it. Wait, I thought for the עולה
olah. you do, you know, two applications of blood, one from the
head and one from the body, no? That's true, that's interesting, but
the head is the only one that, the body is the only
one that matters, so presumably that's the one we're talking about. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says like this, okay, מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu?
So אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, מיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב איכא
בינייהו, mi-tzuy chatas ha-of me'akev ika beinaihu,
whether by the חטאת chatas you had to do the squeezing. תנא
קמא סבר, Tana kamma savar, מיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב, mi-tzuy chatas ha-of
me'akev, you have to squeeze it. וכיון דמיצוי דם עביד, v'keivan d'mi-tzuy
dam avid, if you're going to do the squeezing and then you've
also severed both of the סימנים, simanim, מעשה עולה בחטאת העוף, ma'aseh
olah be-chatas ha-of, you've done exactly what you do by an עולה
olah. to the חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, which is so funny, like
why we assume that that's what invalidates. I mean, I slaughter a
חטאת chatas and I slaughter an אשם, asham, you know, by animal
sacrifices, you know, I do the exact same thing. That doesn't invalidate
until I get to where I put it on the altar. So
why here is the location not enough of a differentiator? I don't
know. But anyway, that's the assumption, that that would invalidate. רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון סבר, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon savar, מיצוי חטאת העוף לא
מעכב. mi-tzuy chatas ha-of lo me'akev. No, you don't have to squeeze
it out. ומחתך בשר בעלמא הוא. u-me-chattech basar be'alma hu.
Okay, so you did more than you needed to, you cut through
some flesh of the bird. Why should that invalidate? Ah, you're making
it just like a עולה? olah, You're not making it like a
עולה. olah You won't squeeze it out, okay? Of course what רש"י
Rashi says is you have to therefore make a point of not
squeezing it out in this case. Okay, fine. So that's one approach,
which is what invalidates it is that it's going to be identical
other than location to how you did the עולה. olah Okay. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava has something that I think is
a little, whatever, different. שהיא בסימן שני בעולת העוף מעכב איכא בינייהו.
she-hi be-siman sheini be-olas ha-of me'akev ika beinaihu.
This is a fascinating conceptual question. Okay, so רבא Rava says like
this, okay, the תורה Torah says sever both סימנים simanim by the
עולה, olah the trachea and the esophagus, okay. Now we know in
normal הלכות שחיטה hilchos shechita that you do not have to slaughter
the second סימן siman of a bird. A bird's שחיטה shechita is
done after you slaughter the first סימן, siman, everybody with me? Whichever
one it is, trachea or esophagus. And you know, so רש"י Rashi
says and also like basically a bird, you know, it dies שחיטה
shechting one סימן siman of it, you know, it'll die quickly. You
don't need it effectively to kill it as the same way. by
a large animal you want to slaughter both in order to kill
it. Okay. So רש״י Rashi says, how do you conceptually think of
the requirement by an עולה olah? to sever the second
סימן, siman, the trachea or esophagus? Do you conceptualize it as the
שחיטה shechita is done, right? I know, מליקה, but whatever. Fundamentally that
act of מליקה is done because that sort of severed it, that
would count as a שחיטה shechita under other circumstances. And now there's
a separate requirement, oh, now that you're done with the מליקה, finish
off by cutting through the rest of the head. That's one way
of thinking about it. The other way of thinking about it is
that we're redefining the parameters of the שחיטה. shechita. By this bird,
it's not considered to be שחט shacht until you sever both. Okay,
what difference would there make between these two
approaches? Everybody hear the difference? The difference would make in a normal
act of שחיטה. shechita. When I'm שוחט shochet an animal, like a
cow, let's say I pause between the trachea and the esophagus and
then I continue doing it. It's invalid. שהייה shehiya invalidates שחיטה shechita
in the middle. Here, what if I pause between my מליקה between
the trachea and the esophagus? If the second סימן siman is part
of the act of שחיטה shechita like by a cow, okay, then
I've invalidated it. If it's a second requirement, not one act, but
a separate thing after you're done with the מליקה, you have to
do a separate thing and finish cutting through, then the pause does
not invalidate. Okay. How is that relevant to this? Because by the
חטאת, chatas there's necessarily a pause because we're going to see that
what you do by
the
חטאת chatas is the following: what you do by חטאת Chatas, is,
again if like I don't know here's my picture. Here's the bird's
like backbone and spinal cord, okay. Here are the סימנים, simanim, okay.
And here you come with your like thumb with your fingernail, okay.
So what your fingernail does, I don't know why that's your long
fingernail, anyway, what your fingernail does is it gets through the backbone
and then it cuts one סימן. siman. Okay, now
when you first go through the back of the neck you can't,
what do you call it, you can't
have cut through most of the flesh of the neck because then
you would have already essentially killed it before you've actually cut the
סימן. siman. Okay, so you first cut through a minority of the
flesh of the neck, then you cut the סימן, siman, and then
you finish cutting through like the majority of the flesh of the
neck, okay. So the point is, and so if the question is
going to be like if here in this case you were to
cut both סימנים, simanim, but between סימן siman one and סימן siman
two you'd be pausing because you'd have to finish cutting through the
majority of the flesh of the neck, okay. So therefore is that
pausing, does that basically
what would that, how do you consider that? So let's take a
look.
רבה Rava אמר amar שהייה shehiya בסימן שני b'Siman sheini בעולת העוף
b'Olas HaOf באוקי be'okei איכא בינייהו. ika bineiyhu. What happens if you
pause by the
עולה olah between סימן siman
one and סימן siman two? תנא קמא Tanna Kamma סבר savar שהייה
shehiya בסימן שני b'Siman sheini בעולת העוף b'Olas HaOf לא lo מעכב.
meakev.
It does not invalidate because it's not really part of the שחיטה,
shechita, it's a requirement. ואף על גב V'af al gav דשהייה deshehiya
קא ka עביד avid מעשה ma'aseh עולה olah. בחטאת. bechatas. And therefore
because here if you were going to cut the second סימן, siman,
the requirement by a חטאת Chatas is after you do סימן siman
one, okay, after you do סימן siman one, the next stage here
is you finish getting רוב rov בשר. basar. You finish cutting through
the majority of the flesh of the neck. And only stage number
three, if you were to choose to do it, would be סימן
siman two, okay. So therefore this cutting both סימנים simanim is going
to be a break between סימן siman one and סימן siman two.
So the question is, what would invalidate a חטאת Chatas by cutting
both סימנים, simanim, that you're making it like an עולה? olah Okay,
but if we say by an עולה olah. there can't be a
pause between one and two, and here we're saying you necessarily have
a pause, then you're going to be safe because it's not going
to be like an עולה. Olah. But if an עולה Olah, is
going to be כשר kasher with a pause, then here it is
going to be invalid because here it is going to be just
like you would do an עולה. Olah. So this is always going
to have a pause if you try to do both סימנים, simanim,
and what would invalidate it would be that that would— make it
like an עולה. Olah So the question is, does an עולה, Olah.
would it be כשר kosher or פסול pasul with a pause? Okay,
so let's read that again. רבא Rava אמר amar שיהא she-yehei בסימן
שני b'Siman sheini בעולת העוף b'Olas HaOf עכב akiv איכא בינייהו. ika
bineiyhu. תנא tanna קמא kama סבר savar שיהא she-yehei בסימן besiman שני
sheni בעולת beolat העוף haof לא lo מעכב. ma-akiv. Pausing would not
invalidate by an עולה. Olah. ואף ve'af על גב gav דשהיה, d'shahiya,
כעביד k'ovid מעשה ma'aseh עולה Olah בחטאת. b'Chatas.
So even by a חטאת, Chatas. even though you're going to pause
between סימן Siman one and two to cut the rest of the
meat of the flesh, you that would have been כשר kosher by
an עולה. Olah, So that makes it invalid by a חטאת Chatas.
because now you're doing by a חטאת Chatas what just which which
something that would have been okay by an עולה. Olah ורבי אליעזר
ברבי שמעון V'Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon סבר savar נמי nami מעכב. ma-akiv.
No, by an עולה Olah if you paused it would be invalid.
וכיון דשהיה V'keivan d'shahiya מחטאת im-Chatas if וכיון דשהיה v'keivan d'shahiya דשהיה
d'shahiya דשהיה d'shahiya דשהיה d'shahiya דשהיה d'shahiya
anyway, since you paused here, so as soon as you pause between
סימן Siman one and סימן Siman two, it stops being like an
עולה, Olah, cause by an עולה Olah that would make it invalid.
And from that stage on, חתיכת chtichas בשר בעלמא basar b'alma הוא,
you're just cutting through flesh. Okay, and that's why it's okay. All
right. אביי Abaye אמר amar and אביי Abaye just says a variation
of this, רוב rov בשר basar מעכב ma-akiv איכא בינייהו. ika bineiyhu.
No, the everybody agrees that pausing presumably by an עולה Olah, would
invalidate. The question is, maybe you don't have to pause by the
חטאת. You're supposed to cut most of the flesh, but if you
didn't and you went straight from סימן Siman one to סימן Siman
two, maybe that would be okay by a חטאת. Okay, so again,
it's a variation. It can't be like an עולה, Olah either an
עולה Olah but if you either but if you pause here and
you're not allowed to pause by an עולה, Olah you're safe. Okay,
so that assumes you're not allowed to pause by an עולה Olah.
and if you pause here you're safe. Or we could say, you're
not allowed to pause by an עולה Olah? and the debate here
is whether you have to pause, maybe you're allowed to go straight
on to סימן Siman two without pausing. All right, and the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ובפלוגתא, U-b'plugta,
this is tied into the other another debate דרבי זירא d'Rabbi Zeira
ורב שמואל בר רב יצחק. v'Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak. חד Had
אמר amar שיהא she-yehei בסימן besiman שני sheni בעולת beolat העוף haof
מעכב ma-akiv איכא בינייהו. ika bineiyhu One says what their debate is
that everybody agrees you have to pause by חטאת because you have
to after סימן Siman one you have to cut most of the
flesh and therefore what they're debating is would a pause invalidate by
an עולה Olah, איכא בינייהו ika bineiyhu. מכלל michlal דבעינן d'ba'inan דרוב
d'rov בשר. basar. Okay, איכא בינייהו. ika bineiyhu. וחד Had אמר amar
רוב rov בשר basar מעכב ma-akiv איכא ika בינייהו. beiniyahu.
No, they they all agree that a pause a pause invalidates and
the question here is whether there has to be a pause. Do
you actually need to cut the majority of the flesh? All right,
so we'll end here. Again, just repeat that I did that at
the end a little bit fast, but just repeat it. Is it
going to be invalid if you cut both סימנים? Simanim? So the
basically the assumption is it's the reason it's invalid is not because
it's a violation of the verse. The reason it would be invalid
is because it's just like an עולה. Olah So the question is,
what would make it just like an עולה? Olah So one way
that they might be debating it is, do you have to squeeze
out the blood? If you don't have to squeeze out the blood,
it doesn't have to be like an עולה, Olah because an עולה
Olah. you squeezed out the blood. The other way they're invalidating it
which is more interesting conceptualizing the act of מליקה is that by
an עולה Olah you cut both trachea and esophagus. Is it that
that's a one act and you can't pause and it's all a
new type of a שחיטה, shechitah, or is the second thing conceptually
a distinct act that you have to do and you're allowed to
pause? So if you're allowed to pause by an עולה Olah. and
you're pausing here, that invalidates. Okay, so that's one version. So that
invalidates because it's making it like an עולה. Olah If you're not
allowed to pause by an עולה Olah and here you necessarily pause
to cut the most of the flesh between סימן Siman one and
סימן Siman two, then you're safe, it's not like an עולה. Olah
So that's one way of understanding it. So here you're not allowed
to pause, here by necessity you pause, that makes you safe. That's
one way. Okay. Or, and the other opinion is by an עולה
you're also allowed to pause. The other way of saying it is
everybody by agrees an עולה you're not allowed to pause, okay, and
then the question though here is okay, but here it's possible is
it possible to do it without pausing? Maybe you don't have to
cut the majority of the flesh. And if it's possible to do
it without pausing, then again you could do this just like an
עולה and that would invalidate it. All right, so we'll end with
this and for now to be continued.